[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine online at computer.org software
signalwire real-time video technology
allows you to create interactive video
experiences that were previously
impossible signalwire gives developers
access to broadcast quality ultra low
latency video for everything from video
collaboration tools for film and tv
studios and fortune 500 enterprises to
engaging virtual events they can even
assist with one-of-a-kind fully
interactive virtual concerts see why the
future of video communication is being
built on signal wire they're easy to
deploy apis and sdks are available in
most popular programming languages
signalwire is a complete unified
platform for integrating video as well
as voice and messaging capabilities into
any application try it today at
signalwire.com and use code se radio for
25 in developer credit go to
signalwire.com that's signalwire.com and
use code se radio to receive 25 in
developer credit today
this is jeremy jung for software
engineering radio today i'm talking to
yusuf striebny he's the author of the
book deployment from scratch a fedora
contributor and he previously worked on
the developer experience team at red hat
yusuf welcome to software engineering
radio thanks for having me i'm really
happy to be here
there are a lot of commercial services
for hosting applications these days
one that's been around for quite a while
is heroku but there's also services like
render and netlify
why should a developer learn how to
deploy from scratch and why would a
developer choose to self-host an
application
i think that
as web engineers and backend engineers
we should know a little bit more how we
run our own applications that you've
write but there is also a business case
right for a lot of people this could be
saving money on hosting especially with
managed databases that can go
high in price very quickly and for
people like me that apart from daily job
have also some side project some will
project they want to
start and maybe turn into a successful
startup you know but it's at the
beginning
so they don't want to spend too much
money on it you know and i can deploy
and serve my little projects from five
dollars virtual private servers in the
cloud
so
i think that's another reason to look
into it
and
business wise if you are let's say a
bigger team and you have the money of
course you can afford all these services
but then what happened to me when i was
leading a startup we were at some flair
and people were coming and asking us we
need to sell their application we don't
trust the club
and then if you want to prepare this
environment for them to host your
application
then you also need to know how to do it
right i understand completely
get the point of not
knowing it because already back in
development can be
huge
you know you can learn so many different
databases languages whatever and
learning also operations and servers it
can be overwhelming i want to say you
don't have to do it all at once just you
know learn a little bit and you can
improve as you go
you will not learn everything in the day
so it sounds like the very first reason
might be to just have a better
understanding of how your applications
are
are running because even if you are
using a service ultimately that is going
to be
running on a bear machine somewhere or
on a virtual machine somewhere so it
could be helpful maybe for
just troubleshooting or better
understanding how your application works
and then there's what you were talking
about with
some companies one to self-host
and just the cost aspect yeah for me
really the primary reason would be to
understand it because you know when i
was starting programming
well first of it was php and i have some
shared hosting to some ftp right and
they would host it for me it was fine
then i switched to ruby on rails and at
the time people were struggling with
deploying it and i was was asking myself
so okay so you run rails s like for
server right it starts in development
but can you just do that on the server
for your production you know can you
just real server and
is that it or is there more to it
or when people were talking about
linux hardening i was like okay but
you know your linux distribution have
some good defaults right so why don't
you need some further hardening but what
does it mean
what's the chance so for me i really
wanted to know
the reason i wrote this book
is that i wanted to like double down on
my understanding that i got it right
yeah i can definitely relate in the
sense that i've also used ruby and ruby
on rails as well
and there's this huge
gap between
just learning how to
run it in a development environment on
your computer versus deploying it onto a
server and it's pretty overwhelming so i
think it's really great that you're
putting together a book that really goes
into a lot of these things that i think
that usually aren't talked about when
people are just talking about learning a
language you can imagine there are a lot
of components you can have into these
applications right you have one database
maybe you have
more databases maybe you have a redis
key value store then you might have load
balancers and all that jazz and i just
want to say that there's one thing i
also say in the book like try to keep it
simple
if you can just deploy in one server if
you don't need to fulfill some sle
up time just do the simplest thing first
because you will really understand it
and when there was an error you will
know how to fix it because when you make
things complex for you then it will be
kind of lost very quickly
so
i try to really make things as simple as
possible to stay on top of them i think
one of the first decisions you have to
make when you're going to self-host an
application is you have to decide which
distribution you're going to use and
there's things like red hat and
ubuntu and debian all these different
distributions
and i'm wondering for somebody who just
wants to deploy their application
whether that's rails django or anything
else
what are the key differences between
them and how should they choose a
distribution if you already know one
particular distribution there's no need
to constantly be on the hunt for a more
shiny thing you know more important that
you know it well and you are not lost
that said there are differences you know
and there could be a long list from
goals and philosophy to who makes it
whether community or company if it's
rolling distribution or not land of
support especially for security updates
the kind of init systems that is used
the kind of c library that is used
packaging format package manager
and for what i think most people will
care about number of packages and their
quality or version right because
essentially linux distribution is
distribution of software
so you care about that software if you
are putting your own stuff
on top of it
you maybe don't care you just
care about it being a linux distribution
and that's it that's fine but if you are
using more things from the distribution
you might starting start carrying a
little bit more you know other thing is
maybe a support for some mandatory
access control or in the you know world
of docker maybe the most minimal image
you can get and start with because you
will be building a lot of a lot of times
the
docker image from the dockerfile
and i would say there are two main
family of systems that people probably
know once based on fedora
and those based on debian
right from fedora you have uh red
enterprise linux and os now uh rookie
linux and on the beyond side you have
ubuntu which is maybe the
most popular cloud distribution right
now
and of course is a fedora packager i'm
kind of in the federal right but if i
can mention two things that i think
makes sense or like
our advantage to federal-based systems
then i would say one is modular packages
because it's traditional systems for a
long time offer only one version
of particular component like what's
equal to sequel
or ruby for one big version so that
means
either it worked for you or it didn't
you know with databases maybe you could
make it work with ruby and python
versions usually you start looking at
some version manager to compile your own
version
because the version was old or you know
simply not the same the one your
application uses and with modular
packages
this changed and now in fedora andreal
and all this we now have several
options to install
there are like four different versions
of postgres sql for instance you know
for different
versions of redis but also different
versions of ruby and python of course
still you don't get
all of the versions you want
so for some people it still might not
work but i think it's a big step forward
because even when i was working at red
hat we were working on a product called
software collections this was kind of
trying to solve this thing for
enterprise customers
but i don't think it was particularly
good solution so i'm quite happy about
this modularity effort you know and i
think the miller packages i look into
them recently are are way better
but i will say one thing don't expect to
use them in a way you use your regular
version manager for
development so if you want to be
switching between versions of different
projects that's not the use case for
them at least as i understand it not for
now you know but for server that's fine
and the second good advantage of
federal-based system i think is good
initial
se linux profile settings
you know se linux is security enhanced
linux what this really is is a mandatory
access control
so
unusual distribution you have a discrete
permissions that you set that user
centered cells on their directories and
files you know but this mandatory access
console means that it's kind of a
profile that is there beforehand that
the administrators prepares
and
it's kind of orthogonal
to those
other security honorees you have there
so that will help you to protect your
most vulnerable processes because
especially with sc linux there are
several modes so there is uh
mlm mode for like that maybe an army
would use you know but for what we use
looks like the default it's some called
targeted policy and that means you are
targeting the vulnerable processes so
that means your services that you are
exposing to external work
like whether it's ssh busker sequel
engine x
all those things so you have a special
profile for them and if someone some
attacker takes over
of your one component one process they
still cannot do much more than what the
component was kind of prepared to do i
think it's really good that we have this
high quality settings already made
because other distributions they might
actually be able to run with sc linux
but they don't necessarily provide you
any starting points you will have to do
all your policies yourself and see linux
is actually quite complex system you
know it's difficult it's even
it's very difficult to use it as a user
kind of if you see some tutorials for
centos you will see a lot of people
mentioning cellulose maybe even turning
it off there's this struggle you know
and that's why i also
use and write
like one big chapter on se linux to get
people more familiar and
less scared about using it and running
with it so se linux is it sounds like
it's basically something where you have
these different profiles for different
types of applications you mentioned
ssh for example maybe there could be one
for nginx or
or one for postgres
and they're basically these collections
of permissions that a process should be
able to have access to whether that's
network ports or
file system permissions things like that
and they're kind of all pre-packaged for
you so you're saying that if you are
using a fedora based distribution you
could say that i want ssh to be allowed
so i'm going to turn on this profile or
i want nginx to be used on this system
so i'm going to turn on this profile and
those permissions are just going to be
applied to the process that needs it is
that correct well actually in the base
system there will be already
a set of base settings that are loaded
you know and you can make your own
policy models that you can load but
essentially it works in a way that
what's not really permitted and allowed
is disallowed that's why it can be a
pain in the ass and as you said you are
completely correct you can imagine it as
an engine x as a reverse proxy
communicating with puma application
server
via a unix socket right
and now
nginx will need to have access to that
socket to be even being able to write to
a unix socket and so on so things like
that but luckily you don't have to know
all these things because it's really
difficult especially if you're starting
out
so there are set of tools and utilities
that will help you to use selenox in a
very convenient way so what you do
what i would suggest you to do is to
run as linux in a permissive mode which
means that it locks any kind of
violations that the application does
against your base system policies right
so you will have them in the lock but
everything will works your application
will work so you don't have to worry
about it and after some time of running
your application you will run these
utilities to analyze
these locks and these violations and
they can even generate a profile for you
so you will know okay this is the
profile
i need this is the extra settings i need
to add once after you do that if there
will be
some problem with your process if some
article will try to do something else
they will be denied detection it will
simply not happen yeah but because of
these utilities you can kind of almost
automate
how you make your profile
and that way it's much easier
so basically the operating system it
comes with all these defaults of things
that you're allowed to do and not
allowed to do you turn on this
permissive flag
and it logs all the things that it would
have blocked if you
were enforcing se linux and then you can
basically go in and add the things that
are that are missing yes exactly right
the next thing i'd like to go into is
one of the things you talk about in the
book is about how your services your
application
how it runs as daemons and i wonder if
you could define what a daemon is
you can think about them as a background
process you know something that
continuously runs in the background even
if the
virtual machine goes down and you reboot
you just want them again to be restarted
and just
run at all times the system is running
and for things like an application you
write or for a database should the
application itself know how to run
itself in the background or is that the
responsibility of some operating system
level process manager
every linux operating system have
actually
a so-called init system
it's actually the second process after
the linux kernel that started on your
system it has a process id of one and
it's essentially the parent of all your
processes because on linux you have
always parents and children
because you are you use forking to make
new processes
and
so this is your system process manager
but obviously
systemd if it's your system process
manager you already trust it with all
the system services you can also trust
it with your application right
i mean who else would you trust even if
you choose some other purchase manager
because there are many
essentially you would have to wrap that
process manager being a system this
service because otherwise
you wouldn't have this connection of
systemdb
supreme supervisor of your application
right when
one of your services travel you want it
to be restarted
and continue so that's what
systemd could do for you if you
kind of design everything as a systemd
service
for
base packages like baseball sql they
already come with a systemd service so
it's very easy to use you just simply
start it and it's running you know and
then for your application you would
write systemd service which is a little
file there are some directives
it's kind of very simple and
straightforward because before before
systemd people were using these services
with bash and it was kind of error prone
but now with systemd it's it's quite
simple they are just a set of directives
that you learn
you tell systemd you know under what
user you should run or what working
directory
you want it to be running with is there
a environment file is there a bit file
and then a few other things the most
important being a directive called exec
start
which tells systemd what process to
start it will start the process and it
will simply oversee it will lock errors
and so on
so in the past i know there used to be
applications that were written where the
application itself would background
itself and basically that would allow
you to run it in the background without
something like a system d
and so it sounds like now
what you should do instead is have your
application
be built to just run in the foreground
and your process manager like system d
can be configured to
handle restarting it which user is
running it environment variables all
sorts of different things that in the
past you might have had to write in your
own bash script or right into the
application itself
and there is also some
other niceties about systemd because
for example you can define how reloading
should work so for instance if you just
change some configuration and you want
to achieve some kind of
zero downtime
change if you can deploy you know you
can tell systemd how this could be
achieved with your process
and if it cannot be achieved because for
instance comma application server it can
for processes and it can actually
it can restart those processes in a way
that it will be zero downtime but when
you want to change the volt puma process
so what do you do
right
and systemd have this nice thing called
circuit activation
and with system visor activation you can
make
another
unit it's not a service unit it's a
socket unit because there are many kind
of you need instantly
and you would basically make a
socket unit that would listen to those
connections and then pass them to the
application
so while application is just starting
and then it could be a completely normal
restart which means stopping starting
then
it will keep the connections open keep
the sockets open and then pass them when
the application is ready to process them
so it sounds like and these sockets
you're referring to these would be
tcp sockets for example of someone
trying to access a website yes but
actually it works with unix
socket as well
so in that example
let's say a user is trying to go to a
website and your service is currently
down you can actually configure
system d to
let the user connect and wait for
another application to come back up and
then hand that connection off to the
application once it's back up yes
exactly that yeah you're basically able
to remove some of the complexity out of
the applications themselves for some of
these special cases and offload those to
system d because yeah otherwise you
would actually need a second server
right you would have to
start second server move traffic there
then upgrade or update your first server
and exchange them back and assistantly
soccer activation you can avoid doing
that and still have this final effect of
zero downtime deployment so this
introduction of system d as the process
manager i think this happened a few
years ago where a lot of linux
distributions moved
to using system d
and there was some
i suppose controversy around that and
i'm kind of wondering if you have any
perspective on why there's some people
who
really didn't want that to happen
you know why that's something people
should worry about or not
yeah there were i think there were
few things
one was for instance the system logging
that suddenly became a binary format
and you need a special utility to read
it you know i mean it's more efficient
it's in a way better but it's not plain
text which all administrators preferred
or very used to so i understand the
concern you know but
it's kind of like
it's fine you know at least to me it's
fine and the second thing that people
consistently force some kind of system
creep
because systemd is trying to do more and
more every year
so
some people say it's not the unix way
systemd should be very minimal in its
system and not do anything else
it's partially true but at the same time
the things that systemd
went into you know i think they are
essentially easier and nice to use and
this is the sustainable services i can
say i i certainly prefer how it's done
now yeah so it sounds like we've been
talking about system d as being this
process manager when the operating
system first boots system d starts and
then it's responsible for starting your
applications or other applications
running on the same
machine but then it's also doing all
sorts of other things like you talked
about that socket activation use case
there's logging i think there's also
scheduled jobs there's like all sorts of
other things that are a part of system d
and that's where
some people disagree on
whether it should be one
application that's handling all these
things
yeah yeah you are right with the
scheduling job like replacing cron you
have now two ways how to do it
but you can still pretty much choose
what you use i mean i still use chrome
so i don't see a
trouble there
you'll see how it goes
one of the things i remember i struggled
with a little bit when i was learning to
deploy applications was
when you're working locally on your
development machine
you
have to install a language runtime in a
lot of cases whether that's for
ruby or python java anything like that
and
when someone is installing on their own
machine they often use something like a
version manager like for example for
ruby there's rb and then
for
node for example there's nvm there's all
sorts of
ways of installing language runtimes and
managing the versions
how should someone set up their language
runtime on a server like would they use
the same tools they use on their
development machine or is it something
yeah so there are several ways you can
do
as i mentioned before with the modular
packages if you find the version there
i would actually recommend to try
to do it with the model package because
the thing is it's so easy to install you
know and it's kind of instant it takes
no time on your server if you just
install this regular package same is
true when building a docker image
because again it will be really fast
so if you can use it i would just use
that because it's like kind of
convenient
but a lot of people will
use some kind of version manager you
know technically speaking they can only
use the installer part like for instance
truly use ruby install
to install new versions right
but then you would have to reference
these full paths to your ruby and where
it is
so what i personally do
i just really set it up as if i'm on the
developer workstation
because for me the mental model of that
is very simple i use the same thing
you know
and
this is true for instance when then you
are referencing what to start in this
exact start directive in systemd you
know
because you have several choices for
instance if you need to start puma you
could be
you could be referencing the address
that is like in your user home dot jam
ruby
version number bin puma
or you can use this version manager they
might have something like true b
exec uh to run with the right version of
ruby and then you pass it the actual
puma puma part and it'll start for you
but what you can also do and
i think it's kind of beautiful you can
do it
is that you can just start bash
with a login shell
and then you just give it the bundle
exec puma command that you would use
normally after logging because if you
install everything normally you know you
have something you know mesh profile
that will load that environment that
will put the right version of ruby and
suddenly it works
and i find it nice because even when you
are later logging in to your box you log
in as that user is that application user
and suddenly you have all that
environment then and just can start
things
as you are used to you know no problem
there
yeah something i've run into the past is
when i would install a language runtime
and like you were kind of describing
i would have to type in the full path to
get to
the ruby runtime or the python runtime
and it sounds like what you're saying is
just install it like you would on your
development machine and then in the
system d configuration file you actually
log into a bash shell and run your
application from the bash shell so it
has access to
all the same things you would have in an
interactive login environment is that
right yeah yeah that's exactly right so
it will be
basically the same thing and
it's kind of easy to reason about it you
know like you can start with that maybe
you will change it later to something
else but
it's a nice way how to do it so you
mentioned
having a user to run your application
and so i'm wondering how you decide
what
linux user
should run your applications are you
creating a separate user for each
application you run like how are you
making those decisions
yes i am actually making a new user for
for my application
well
at least for the part of application
that is the application server and
workers you know so engine xm
might have its own user postgresql might
have its own user you know i'm not like
trying to consolidate that under one
user but in terms of rest application
like whenever i run puma or whenever i
run sidekiq that will be part of that
one user you know application user and i
will appropriately set the right
exercise directories
so it isolated from everything else
and something that i've seen also when
you
are installing
ruby or you're installing some other
language runtime
you have
the
libraries like in the case of ruby
there's gems
and
when you're on your development machine
and you
install these gems these packages they
go into the user's home directory and so
you're able to install and use them
without having
let's say pseudo or root access is that
something that you carry over to
your deployments as well or do you store
your
your libraries and your gems in some
place that's accessible outside of that
user i'm just wondering how you approach
that
i would actually keep it next to my
application this kind of touches maybe
the question or where to put your
application files on the system so
there is something called
fhs
file system hierarchy standard
you know that looks distribution to use
they
of course use it with some little
modifications here and there
and this standard is basically followed
by packages and of course in packaging
you process but other than that it's
kind of random you know it could be a
different path
and it says where certain files should
go so you have slash home you have slash
user b for executables elsewhere for
logs and so on and so on and now when
you
want to put your
your replication file somewhere you are
thinking where to put them right you
have essentially i think like three
options
for one you can put it to home because
as we talked about i set up a dedicated
user for that application so it could
make sense to put it in home
why i don't like putting it at home is
because there are certain
labeling in se linux that kind of makes
your life more difficult
it's not meant to be there essentially
on some other system uh without se linux
i think it worked fine i also did it
before you know it's not like you cannot
do it you can
then you have the
kind of your web server default
locations
you know
like user share engine x html or slash
bar slash www
and these systems will be prepared for
you with all these ac linux labeling so
when you put files there but things were
mostly work
but
i also saw a lot of people do that
because this particular reason what i
don't like about it is
that
if ngx is just my reverse proxy you know
it's not that i am serving the files
from there so i don't like the location
for this reason if it will be just
static website i'll absolutely put it
there that's the best location
then you can put it to some arbitrary
location some new one that's not
conflicting if anything else you know
if you want to follow the call system
hierarchy standard you put it to slash
srv you know and then maybe slash name
of the application or
your domain name hostname
you can choose what you like
so that's what i do now i simply do it
from scratch to this location
and
as part of the
se linux i simply
make a module make a profile
and allow all these paths to work
and so to answer your question where i
would put this gems it would actually go
to this directory it would be like slash
app
gems for instance
there's a few different places people
could put their application they could
put it in the user's home folder but you
were saying because of the built-in se
linux rules sc linux is going to
basically fight you on that and prevent
you from doing a lot of things
in that folder
what you've chosen to do is to create
your own folder that i guess you
described it as being somewhat arbitrary
just being a folder that you
consistently are going to use in all
your projects and then you're going to
configure se linux to allow you to run
whatever you want to run from this
custom folder that you've decided yeah
you can say that you
do almost the same amount of work for
home or some other location but simply
find it cleaner to do it this way and in
a way even fulfill the fhs suggestion
to put it to slash srv but yeah it's
completely arbitrary you can choose
anything else uh cis admins
choose
www or
whatever they like and it's fine it will
work there's no problem there
and for the gems actually they could be
in home you know
but
i just insert bundler to put it to that
location next to my application okay
rather than having a common folder for
multiple applications to pull your
libraries or your gems from you have it
installed in the same place as the
application and that just keeps all your
dependencies in the same place yeah and
the example you're giving you're putting
everything in slash srv
slash and then maybe the name of your
application is that right
yeah okay yeah because i've noticed that
just looking at different
systems i've seen people install things
into opt
installed into slash srv and it can just
be kind of
tricky as somebody who's starting out to
know where am i supposed to put this
stuff so so basically it sounds like
just
pick a place and at least if it's in
slash srv then sys admins who are
familiar with the standard file system
hierarchy will know to look in there
yeah yeah all pt is also a common
location as you say
or you know if it's actually a packaged
web application for the right can even
be in such users like share you know so
it might not be necessarily in locations
we talked about before
sc radio listeners we want to hear from
you
please visit se-radio.net
survey to share a little information
about your professional interests and
listening habits it takes less than two
minutes to help us continue to make se
radio even better
your responses to the survey are
completely confidential that's
s-e-radio.net survey
thanks for your support of the show we
look forward to hearing from you soon
[Music]
one of the things you cover in the book
is setting up a deployment system and
you're using
shell scripts in the case of the book
and i was wondering how you decide when
shell scripts are sufficient and when
you should consider more specialized
tools like ansible or
chef puppet things like that yeah i
chose bash in the book because you get
to see things without obstructions you
know if i would be using let's say
ansible then suddenly we are writing
some yaml files
and
you are using a lot of python modules
that ansible use and you don't really
know what's going on
at all times so you learn to do things
with ansible
2.0 let's say
and then new ansible comes out and
you have to learn what you did you know
and i would have to rewrite the book
but the thing is that with just bash i
can show
literally just bash commands like okay
you run this and this happens and
another thing i use it is that you
realize how simple something can be
like you can have a
super cool cluster
with ssh and whatever
in maybe 20 mesh commands around that so
it's not necessarily
that difficult and it's much easier to
actually
understand it if it's just those 20 mesh
commands i also think that learning a
little bit more about bash is actually
quite beneficial because you encounter
them in various of places i mean rpm
spec files like the packages are built
that's bash you know
language version managers like pi and
rbf death bash if you want to tweak it
if you have a bug there
you might look into source code and try
to fix it you know it will be bash then
docker files are essentially bash you
know their entry points gives my brush
so it's not like you can do the avoid
bash so maybe learning a little bit just
a little bit more than you know and be a
little bit more comfortable i think it
can get you a long way because even i am
not a some bash programmer you know i
would never call myself like that also
consider this like you can have a full
featured rails application maybe in 200
lines of bash code up and running
somewhere you can understand it in the
afternoon so for a small deployment i
think it's quite refreshing to use bash
and some people miss out on not just
doing the first simple thing possible
that they can do
but obviously when you go like more team
members more complex applications or a
suite of applications things get
difficult very fast with bash so
obviously most people will end up with
some high level tool
it can be ansible it can be chef it
might be kubernetes you know so
my philosophy again is just to keep it
simple if i can do something with bash
and it's like 100 lines i will do this
back because when i come back to it even
after three years
it will work and i can directly see what
i have to fix you know if there is a
public sql update at this new location
whatever i immediately know where to
look
and what to change
and with high level tooling you kind of
have to stay on top of them the new
versions and
updates
so
that's that mesh is very limited but
it's kind of refreshing for very small
deployment you want to do for yourself
yeah so it sounds like from a learning
perspective it's beneficial because you
can see line by line and it's code you
wrote and you know exactly what each
thing does
but also it sounds like
when you have a project that's
relatively small maybe there there
aren't a lot of different servers or the
deployment process isn't too complicated
you actually choose to start with bash
and then only move to
something more complicated like ansible
or even kubernetes once your project has
gotten to a certain size you would see
it in the book i even explained a
multiple server deployment using bash
where you can actually keep
your components like kind of separate so
like your database have its own
lifecycle if it's on deploy script then
your load balancer the same and even
when you have application servers maybe
you have more of them
so the nice thing is that when you
first write your first script to
provision one server configure one
server then you simply write another
supervising script that would call this
single script
just in the loop
and you will change the server variable
to change the ip address or something
and suddenly you can deploy to more of
course it's very basic and it's uh you
know it doesn't have some any kind of
parallelization to it or whatever
but if you have like free application
servers you can do it and you understand
it almost immediately you know if you
are already a software engineer there is
almost nothing to understand and
you can just start and keep going
and
when you're deploying to servers a lot
of times you're dealing with credentials
whether that's private keys passwords or
keys to third-party apis and when you're
working with this
self-hosted environment working with
bash scripts i was wondering
what you use to store your credentials
and how those are managed
i use a desktop application called
password save
that can save my passwords and whatever
and you can also put their ssh keys and
so on and then i simply
can do
a backup of these keys and of this
password to some other secure physical
location but basically i don't use any
service online for that i mean they are
services for that especially for teams
and in clouds especially because they
might have their own services for that
but for me personally
again i just keep it as simple as i can
it's just on my
my computer maybe my hard disk and
that's it
nowhere else
so would this be a case of where on your
local machine for example you might have
a file that defines all the environment
variables for each server
you don't check that into your source
code repository but when you run your
bash scripts maybe you read from that
file and
use that and deploying to the server
generally speaking
yes but i think with rails there's a
nice option to use their encrypted
credentials so basically then you can
commit all these securities together
with your app and the only thing you
need to
keep to yourself is just like one
variable
so it's much more easy to store it and
keep it safe because it's just one thing
and everything else you keep inside your
repository i know for sure there are
other
programs that behave in the same way
that can be used with different stacks
that doesn't have this back end because
rares have it back in but if you are
using django if you are using alexa or
whatever then they don't have it but i
know that there are some programs i
don't remember the names right now
but they essentially allow you to do
exactly the same thing to just commit it
to source control but in a secure way
because it's encrypted
yeah that's an interesting solution
because you always hear about people
checking in passwords and keys
into their source code repository and
then
you know it gets exposed online somehow
but in this case like you said it's
encrypted and
only your machine has the key so
that actually allows you to use the
source code to store all that yeah i
think for teams you know for more
complete deployments there are various
tools from hashicorp vault you know to
some call providers things but
you can really
start and keep it very very simple for
logging an application that you're
self-hosting there's a lot of different
managed services that exist
but i was wondering what you use in a
self-hosted environment and whether your
applications are logging to standard out
whether they're writing the files
themselves i was wondering how you
typically approach it yeah so
there are a lot of logs you can have
right from system log to your web server
log application log database log
whatever
and you somehow need to stay on top of
them because when you have one server
it's quite fine to just login in
and look around but when there are more
servers involved it's kind of a pain
and so people start to look in something
so as logging system
i think when you are more mature you
would look to things like
datadock right or you will build
something of your own on elasticstack
that's what we do on the project i'm
working right now
but
i kind of think that there is some
upfront cost uh setting it all up you
know and in terms of some looking with
elastic stack you are essentially
building your logging application even
you can say you know it's a lot of work
i also want to say that
you don't look into your locks
all that often especially if you set up
proper error and performance monitoring
which is what i do with my project it's
one of the first things i do
so those are services like drawbar and
skylight and there are some that you can
self-host so if people want to sell them
they can but i find it kind of
easier to even though i'm supposing my
application to just rely on this hosted
solution
like drillbar skylight up signal you
know and i have to say especially i
started to like upset now recently
because they kind of bundle everything
together
when you have trouble with your
self-hosting the last thing you want to
find yourself in a situation when
your self-hosted logs and solid error
reporting also went down and doesn't
work
you know
so although i like self-hosting my
application
i kind of like to
offload this responsibility to some
hosted hosted providers
yeah so i think that in and of itself is
a interesting
topic to cover because we've mostly been
talking about self-hosting your
applications and you were just saying
how
logging might be something that's
actually better to use a managed service
i was wondering if there's other
services for example
cdns or other things where it actually
makes more sense for you to let somebody
else host it rather than yourself
i think that depends logging for me is
obvious
and then i think a lot of developers
kind of fear databases so they rather
have some kind of one-click database you
know replication and all that just
backed in so i think a lot of people
would go for managed database
although it may be one of those pricey
services it also likes one that actually
gives you a lot of peace of mind you
know
maybe i would just like point out that
even though you get all these automatic
backups and so on maybe you should still
try to make your own backup just for
sure you know even someone promised
something uh your data is usually the
most valuable thing you have in your
application
so you should not lose it and some
people will go maybe for load balancers
because it may be easy to start like
let's say on digital ocean you know you
just click it and it's there
but if you go opposite direction if you
for instance decide to sell your
load balancer it can also give you more
options what to do with that right
because you can configure it differently
you can even configure it to be a backup
server if all of your application
servers go down which is maybe could be
interesting use case right if you mess
up and
your application servers are not running
because you were just messing with with
them suddenly it's okay because your old
balances just take some traffic right
and you can do that if it's your little
answer
the ones hosted are
sometimes limited so i think it comes to
also even with the databases you know
it's like
maybe you use some kind of extension
that is simply not available that kind
of makes you
self-host something
but if they offer exactly what you want
and it's really easy you know then
maybe you just
you just do it and that's why i think i
kind of like deploying to
virtual machines in the cloud because
you can mix and match all these services
the way you want and that always change
the configurations to
match your needs and i find that quite
nice
one of the things you talk about near
the end of your book is how you start
with a single server you have the
database the application the web server
everything
on the same machine
and i wonder if you could talk a little
bit about
how
far you can take that one server and why
people should consider starting with
that approach
it depends a lot on your application for
instance i write applications that are
quite simple in nature i don't have so
many sql calls in one page and so on
but the applications i worked for before
sometimes they are quite heavy and you
know even
with little traffic they suddenly need a
more beefy server you know so it's
a lot about application but there are
certainly
a lot of good examples out there for
instance
the team from x-plane flight simulator
they just deployed to one one server you
know the wall backhand all those flying
players because it's essentially simple
and they even use elixir which is
based on bmvm which means it's great for
concurrency for distributed systems it's
great for multiple servers but they
still deploy to one because it's simple
and they use the second only when they
do
update to the service and otherwise they
go back to one another one would be
maybe a peterslavos like maker that
already has like one million dollar
business and it's
he has all of his projects on one server
you know because it's enough why you
need to make it complicated you can go
and a very profitable service and you
might not leave one server it's not a
problem
another good example i think is stack
overflow they have
i think they have some page but they
exactly show you what servers they are
running they have multiple servers
but the thing is they have only a few
servers you know
so those are the examples that goes
against maybe the trend of spinning up
hundreds of servers in the cloud which
you can do a bit easier when you have to
auto scaling because you can just go
little by little
you know but i don't see the point of
having more servers to me it means more
work
if i can do it with one i do it with one
but i would mention one thing to pay
attention to when you are on one server
you don't want suddenly your background
workers exhaust all the cpu
so that your database cannot serve your
queries anymore
right
so for that i recommend looking into
control groups or c groups on linux when
you create a simple slice where you
define how much cpu power and how much
memory can be used for that service
and then you attach it to
to some processes you know and when we
are talking about system d services
they actually have this one directive
where you specify your c group slice
and then
when you have this worker server and
maybe it even forks because it it runs
some utilities right for you to process
images or what so
then it will be all contained within
that c group
so it will not influence the other
services you have
and you can say okay you know i give
worker service only 20 of my cpu power
because i don't care if they make it
fast or not
it's not important important is that
every visitor still gets its page you
know and if they are working waiting for
some background processing they will
wait and your service is not going down
yeah so it sort of sounds like the
difference between if you have a whole
bunch of servers then you have to
have some way of managing all those
servers whether that's kubernetes or
something else whereas an alternative to
that is having one server or just a few
servers
but going a little bit deeper into the
capabilities of the operating system
like the c groups you were referring to
where you could
specify how much cpu how much ram and
things for each service on that same
machine to use so it's kind of
changing
i don't know if it's removing work but
it's changing the type of work you're
doing
yeah you essentially
maybe have to think about it
more in a way of this case of splitting
the memory or cpu power
but also it enables you to use for
instance unique sockets instead of tcp
sockets and they are faster
you know so
in a way it can be also an advantage for
you in some cases to actually keep it on
one server and of course you don't have
a network trip so another saving so
together that service will be faster as
long as it's running and there's no
problem it will be faster
and for
high availability
yeah it's obviously a problem if you
have just one server but
you also have to think about it in more
complex way to be high available with
all your components from load balancers
to databases you suddenly have a lot of
servers you know to take care and that
setup might be complex might be fragile
and maybe you are better off with just
one server that you can quickly spin up
again so for instance there's any
problem with your server you get alert
and you simply make new one you know and
if you can configure it within
20 30 minutes
maybe it's not a problem maybe even you
are still fulfilling your service level
contract for uptime so
i think if i can go this way i prefer it
simply because it's so much easy to
think about it like that this might be a
little difficult to answer but when you
look at the projects where you've
self-hosted them
versus the projects where
you've gone
all in on say aws
and when you're trying to troubleshoot a
problem do you find that it's
easier when
you're troubleshooting
things on a vm that you set up or do you
find it easier to troubleshoot when
you're working with something that's
connecting a bunch of managed
services absolutely i find it much
easier to debug anything i set up myself
especially with one server it's even
easier but simply the fact that you
build it yourself
means that you know how it works and at
any time you can go and fix your problem
you know this is what i found a problem
with services like digitalocean
marketplace i don't know how they call
this self
hosted apps that you can like one click
and have your real estate and go up up
and running i actually used when i
wasn't that skilled with linux and
self-hosting i use only distribution
called
a turnkey linux it's the same idea you
know it's like that they prepare
the profile for you and then you can
just easily run it as if it's a
completely hosted thing like heroku
but actually it's your server and you
have to pay attention but i actually
don't like it because you didn't set it
up you don't know how it's set up you
don't know if it has some problems some
security issues and especially the
people that come from these services
they end up running something
and they don't know
i believe they don't know because when i
was running it i didn't know
right
so they are not even know what they are
running so
if you really don't want to care about
it i think it's completely fine there's
nothing wrong with that but just go for
that gender or heroku and make your life
easier you know
yeah it sounds like the solutions where
it's like a one-click install on your
own infrastructure you get the bad parts
of both like you get the bad parts of
having this machine that you need to
manage but you didn't set it up so
you're not really sure how to manage it
you don't have that team at amazon who
can fix something for you because
ultimately it's still your machine so
that could have some issues there
yeah yeah exactly i would not recommend
it or if you really decide to do it at
least really look inside you know try to
understand it try to learn it then it's
fine
but just to spin it up and hope for the
best it's not the way to go
in the book you cover a few different
things that you use such as
ruby on rails and nginx redis postgres
i'm assuming that the things you would
choose for applications you build and
self-host you want them to have as
little maintenance as possible because
you're the one who's responsible for all
of it
i'm wondering if there's any other
applications that you consider a part of
your default stack that you can depend
on and that the maintenance burden is is
low
yeah so
that's exactly right if i can i would
rather
minimize the amount of dependencies i
have
so for instance i would think twice of
using let's say elasticsearch even
though i used it before
and it's great for what it can do
if i can avoid it maybe i would try to
avoid it you know you can have decent
full text search with postgres today
so as long as it would work i would
personally avoid it
i think
one relation
database let's say that this is kind of
necessary you know i work a lot with
alex recently so
we don't use redis for instance so it's
quite nice that you can limit uh limit
the number of dependencies by just
choosing a different stack
although then you have to
write your application in a little
different way so sometimes even
in circumstances this could be useful
you know i think
it's not difficult to run it so i don't
see a problem there i would just say
that with the services like
elasticsearch they might not come with a
good authentication option
for instance i think elasticsearch
offers it but not in the free version
you know
so i would just like to say that if you
are deploying a component like that be
aware of it that you cannot just keep it
completely open to the world
you know and maybe if you don't want to
pay for
a version that has it or maybe you are
using a database it doesn't have it
completely
you could maybe build a just a little
bit tiny proxy that would just do
authentication and pass this request
back and forth that's what you could do
you know but just not forget that you
might join something unauthenticated i
was wondering if there is any other
applications or capabilities where
you would typically
hand off to a managed service rather
than trying to deal with yourself
oh sending emails not because it's hard
it's actually surprisingly easy to start
sending your own emails but the problem
is the deliverability part right
you want your emails to be delivered
and i think it's because of the amount
of spam everybody's sending
it's very difficult to get into people's
boxes you know you simply be flagged you
have some unknown address it will just
not work so actually building up some
history of some
ip address it could take a while it
could be very annoying just and you
don't even know how to debug it you you
cannot really write google hey i'm just
like this nice little server so just
consider me you cannot do that so i
think it's a kind of a travel so i would
say for email definitely there's another
thing that just go with a hosted option
you might still configure
your server to be sending up emails that
could be useful for instance if you want
to do some
little thing like scanning your system
log and when you see some troublesome
logging you know that shouldn't happen
or something and maybe you just want an
alert you want email to be sent to you
that something fishy is going on and so
you can still set up even your
server not just your main application it
might have a nice library for that you
know to send that email but you will
still need this so-called relay server
you will just pass your email further
yeah because building this trust and
email world that's not something i would
do and i don't think as a you know
independent indie maker developer you
can really have resources to do
something like that
so that'll be a perfect example for that
yeah yeah i think that's probably a good
place to start wrapping up but is there
anything we missed that you think we
should have talked about
i think we kind of covered it maybe we
didn't talk much about containers
that a lot of people nowadays use maybe
i would just like to point out one thing
with containers is that
you can
again do just very minimal approach to
adopting containers you know you don't
need to go full-on containers at all you
can just run a little service maybe your
workers in a container for example if i
want to run something as part of my
application
the upstream the developers that develop
this one component already provide a
docker file it's very easy way to start
right because you just deployed their
image
and
you run it that's it and you don't have
to learn what kind of different stack it
is is it java is it bison how i would
run it so maybe you care for your own
application but when you have to just
take something that is already made and
it has a docker image you just really
nice way to start and one more thing i
would like to mention is that you also
don't really need using services like
docker hub you know well most people
would use it to host their artifacts
their build images so they can quickly
pull them up and start them on many many
servers and blah blah but if you have
just one server like me
but you want to use containers a nice
thing is to just you know push the
container directly
you essentially it's just an archive
in that archive there are a few folders
they represent the layers that's the
layers you build it and the docker file
and that's it you can just move it
around like that and you don't need any
external services to
run your containerized little service
yeah i think that's a good point because
a lot of times when you hear people
talking about
containers it's within the context of
kubernetes and
you know that's a whole other thing you
have to learn you have to learn not only
how containers work but you have to
learn how to
deploy kubernetes how to work with that
and i think it's good to remind people
that it is possible to just choose a few
things run them as containers
you don't need to
like you said even run everything as
containers you can just try a few things
yeah exactly
where can people check out the book and
where can they follow you and see what
you're up to so they can just go to
deploymentfromscratch.com
that's like the homepage for the book
and if they want to follow up they can
find me on twitter
that would be
slash
str
z i b n y
j
like steven j
and i tried to put updates there but
also some news from
ruby alex here linux world so
they can follow along
i had a chance to read through the alpha
version of the book and there's a lot of
really good information in there i think
it's something that
i wish i had had when i was starting out
because
there's
so much that's not really talked about
like when you go
look online for how to
learn django or how to learn ruby on
rails or things like that they teach you
how to build the application how to run
it on your laptop but there's this very
large gap between
what you're doing on your laptop and
what you need to do to get it running on
a server so i think anybody who's
interested in learning more about how to
deploy their own application or even how
it's done in general i think they'll
find the book really valuable yeah thank
you thank you for saying that it makes
me really happy and as you say that's
the idea i really packed like kind of
everything
you need in that book and i just use
back so it's easier to follow and keep
it without any abstractions and then
maybe you will learn
some other tools and you will apply the
concepts but you can do whatever you
want
all right well youssef thank you so much
for talking to me today thank you jeremy
this has been jeremy jung for software
engineering radio thanks for listening
sc radio listeners we want to hear from
you
please visit se radio.net slash survey
to share a little information about your
professional interests and listening
habits it takes less than two minutes to
help us continue to make se radio even
better
the responses to the survey are
completely confidential that's
s-e-radio.net slash survey
thanks for your support of the show we
look forward to hearing from you soon
[Music]
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of se radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening